Well, good afternoon.
مساء الخير
How many of you
كم شخص منكم
took the ALS Ice Bucket Challenge?
شارك في تحدي دلو الثلج؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Woo hoo!
مرحــــا!
Well, I have to tell you, from the bottom of our hearts,
أود ان أشكركم من أعماق قلبي
thank you so very, very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم
Do you know to date the ALS Association
هل تعلمون أنه حتى الآن منظمة التصلب الجانبي الضموري ALS
has raised 125 million dollars?
قامت بجمع 125 مليون دولار من التبرعات؟
Woo hoo! (Applause)
مرحــــا! (تصفيق)
It takes me back to the summer of 2011.
وهذا يعود بي إلى صيف 2011.
My family, my kids had all grown up.
لقد كبرت عائلتي
We were officially empty nesters,
وأصبحت وحيدة مع زوجي
and we decided, let's go on a family vacation.
لذلك قرّرنا قضاء إجازة عائلية.
Jenn, my daughter, and my son-in-law
إبنتي جين وصهري
came down from New York.
قدموا من مدينة نيويورك.
My youngest, Andrew,
إبني الأصغر، أندرو،
he came down from his home in Charlestown
قدم من منزله في تشارليستون
where he was working in Boston,
حيث مكان عمله في مدينة بوسطن،
and my son Pete,
وابني بيت
who had played at Boston College, baseball,
الذي سبق له أن لعب البيسبول في جامعة بوسطن
had played baseball professionally in Europe,
ولعبها ببطولات إحترافية في أروبا
and had now come home and was selling group insurance, he also joined us.
والآن قد عاد إلى بلده وأصبح يعمل بوكالة لتأمين الشركات،
And one night, I found myself
وقد إنضم إلينا هو الآخر
having a beer with Pete,
وفي ليلة، وجدت نفسي جالسة مع بيت
and Pete was looking at me and he just said,
وبينما هو يحدق إلي قال لي
"You know, Mom, I don't know,
"أتعرفين يا أمي،"
selling group insurance is just not my passion."
"لا أظن أن العمل بوكالة التأمين يناسبني."
He said, "I just don't feel I'm living up to my potential.
لقد قال، "لا أشعر أنني أعيش لتحقيق قدراتي.
I don't feel this is my mission in life."
لا أشعر أن عملي هذا هو مهمتي في الحياة."
And he said, "You know, oh by the way, Mom,
لقد قال، "أتعرفين، بالمناسبة يا أمي،
I have to leave early from vacation
يجب أن أنهي الإجازة باكرا
because my inter-city league team that I play for made the playoffs,
لأن فريقي الذي ألعب معه وصل إلى التصفيات النهائية
and I have to get back to Boston because I can't let my team down.
لذلك يجب عليَ العودة إلى بوسطن لكي لا أخيِّب أمل فريقي.
I'm just not as passionate about my job
أنا فقط لست شغوفا بعملي،
as I am about baseball."
كما أنا شغوفٌ بلعبة البيسبول."
So off Pete went, and left the family vacation —
وبالتَالي ذهب بيت، وترك الإجازة العائلية
break a mother's heart —
ترك أمه في حسرة
and he went, and we followed four days later
قمنا باللحاق به بعد أربعة أيام
to see the next playoff game.
لمشاهدة فريقه يلعب التصفيات النهائية.
We're at the playoff game, Pete's at the plate,
وداخل المبارة وبينما بيت في الملعب
and a fastball's coming in,
وجاءت كرة سريعة
and it hits him on the wrist.
وضربته في رسغه
Oh, Pete.
آهٍ يا بيت.
His wrist went completely limp, like this.
إرتهل رسغه كلياً، هكذا.
So for the next six months,
لذلك في السّتة أشهر المقبلة،
Pete went back to his home in Southie,
عاد بيت إلى منزله في جنوب بوسطن،
kept working that unpassionate job,
استمر في العمل الفاتر،
and was going to doctors
وقد كان يذهب لإستشارة الأطباء
to see what was wrong with this wrist
ليرى ماذا حل برسغه
that never came back.
الذي لم يعد لحالته الطبيعية.
Six months later, in March,
ستة أشهر لاحقاً، في مارس،
he called my husband and me, and he said,
إتصل بي و بزوجي، وقال،
"Oh, Mom and Dad, we have a doctor
"أمي، أبي، لقد وجدنا طبيبا
that found a diagnosis for that wrist.
يمكنه تشخيص مشكلة رسغي.
Do you want to come with the doctor's appointment with me?"
هل تريدون الذهاب معي إلى موعد الطبيب؟"
I said, "Sure, we'll come in."
فقلت له، "سنذهب معك بالتأكيد."
That morning, Pete, John and I
في ذلك الصباح، أنا وبيت وجون
all got up, got dressed, got in our cars —
إستيقظنا، غيرنا ملابسنا وركبنا في السيارات
three separate cars
ثلاث سيارات مختلفة
because we were going to go to work
لأننا كنا ذاهبين إلى العمل
after the doctor's appointment to find out what happened to the wrist.
بعد موعد الطبيب لمعرفة ماذا حدث لرسغ بيت.
We walked into the neurologist's office, sat down,
دخلنا إلى مكتب طبيب الأمراض العصبية، وجلسنا
four doctors walk in,
ودخل أربعة أطباء
and the head neurologist sits down.
وجلس الطبيب المسؤول
And he says, "Well, Pete, we've been looking at all the tests,
وقال "حسنا بيت، لقد قمنا بدراسة جميع الاختبارات
and I have to tell you, it's not a sprained wrist,
وعليً اخبارك، انه ليس التواء في المعصم
it's not a broken wrist,
ولا حتى كسر في المعصم
it's not nerve damage in the wrist,
ولا حتى تضرر اعصاب المعصم
it's not an infection,
وانه ليس عدوى
it's not Lyme disease."
ولا مرض لايم
And there was this deliberate elimination going up,
الاحتمالات اصبحت محدودة شيئا فشيئا
and I was thinking to myself,
وفكرت في نفسي
where is he going with this?
الى ماذا يريد ان يصل الطبيب ؟
Then he put his hands on his knees,
ثم وضع يديه على ركبتيه
he looked right at my 27-year-old kid, and said,
ونظر مباشرة لابني ذو الـ 27 عاما، وقال
"I don't know how to tell a 27-year-old this:
لا اعلم كيف ساستطيع اخبار شخص بعمر الـ 27 هذا:
Pete, you have ALS."
بيت، انت مصاب بمرض الـ ALS
ALS?
ALS ؟
I had had a friend whose 80-year-old father had ALS.
والد احد اصدقائي بعمر الـ 80 كان مصاب بالـ ALS
I looked at my husband, he looked at me,
نظرت الى زوجي، وهو نظر الي
and then we looked at the doctor, and we said, "ALS?
ونظرنا الى الطبيب وقلنا: ALS ؟
Okay, what treatment? Let's go.
حسنا، هيا ، ماهو العلاج
What do we do? Let's go."
هيا، ماذا علينا ان نفعل
And he looked at us, and he said, "Mr. and Mrs. Frates,
نظر الينا الطبيب وقال: سيد وسيدة فريتس
I'm sorry to tell you this,
اسف لاخباركم بهذا
but there's no treatment and there's no cure."
ولكن لا يوجد علاج، ولا يوجد شفاء من هذا المرض حتى الان
We were the worst culprits.
لقد كنا منصدمين للغاية
We didn't even understand
حتى اننا لم نفهم
that it had been 75 years since Lou Gehrig
منذ اصابة لاعب البيسبول لوو جيرغ منذ 75عاما
and nothing had been done in the progress against ALS.
ولم يحدث اي تقدم للشفاء من مرض الـ ALS
So we all went home, and Jenn and Dan
لذا عدنا جميعا للمنزل، واتبعنا جين ودان
flew home from Wall Street,
من الوول ستريت
Andrew came home from Charlestown,
وجاء اندرو للمنزل من شارليستون
and Pete went to B.C. to pick up
وذهب بيت لاحضار
his then-girlfriend Julie and brought her home,
صديقته جولي للمنزل
and six hours later after diagnosis,
وبعد ست ساعات من المعاينة
we're sitting around having a family dinner,
كنا جالسين في غداء عائلي
and we're having small chat.
وحظينا ببعض المحادثة
I don't even remember cooking dinner that night.
حتى أنني لا اتذكر طهي الطعام تلك الليلة
But then our leader, Pete, set the vision,
ثم قائدنا بيت، وضع لنا الخطة
and talked to us just like we were his new team.
وتحدث الينا وكأننا فريقه الجديد
He said, "There will be no wallowing, people."
وقال: "لا مكان لليأس يا جماعة"
He goes, "We're not looking back,
"نحن لا ننظر للوراء"
we're looking forward.
"نحن ننظر للأمام"
What an amazing opportunity we have to change the world.
"لدينا فرصة رائعة لتغيير العالم"
I'm going to change the face
"سأقوم بتغيير"
of this unacceptable situation of ALS.
الحالة الغير مقبولة لمرض الـ ALS
We're going to move the needle,
سأحرك البوصلة
and I'm going to get it in front of philanthropists like Bill Gates."
وسأقوم بعرض الامر على المتبرعين كـ بيل غيتس
And that was it. We were given our directive.
وهكذا بدأت، قمنا بوضع خطة
So in the days and months that followed,
وفي الايام و الشهور التي لحقت ذلك
within a week, we had our brothers and sisters
خلال اسبوع انضم الينا اشقائنا
and our family come to us,
وعائلتنا انضمت الينا
that they were already creating Team Frate Train.
وشكلنا فرق الأخوة
Uncle Dave, he was the webmaster;
العم ديف كان المسؤول عن الموقع
Uncle Artie, he was the accountant;
العم أرتي كان المحاسب
Auntie Dana, she was the graphic artist;
دانة كانت مصممة الغرافيكس
and my youngest son, Andrew,
وابني الاصغر اندرو
quit his job, left his apartment in Charlestown
استقال من عمله، وترك منزله في شارليستون
and says, "I'm going to take care of Pete and be his caregiver."
وقال: "أنا ساهتم ببيت وسأقوم برعايته"
Then all those people, classmates, teammates,
وكل هؤلاء الأشخاص من أصدقاء
coworkers that Pete had inspired
وزملاء عمل، الذين قام بيت بالهامهم
throughout his whole life,
خلال حياته
the circles of Pete all started intersecting with one another,
جميع معارف بيت بدأوا بالتعارف
and made Team Frate Train.
وشكلو فريق الأخوة
Six months after diagnosis,
بعد ستة أشهر من المعاينة
Pete was given an award at a research summit for advocacy.
منح بيت جائزة في مؤتمر بحثي للتأييد
He got up and gave a very eloquent speech,
وقام بالقاء خطاب بليغ للغاية
and at the end of the speech, there was a panel,
وبعد نهاية الخطاب كان هناك هيئة خبراء
and on the panel were these pharmaceutical executives
و هيئة الخبراء احتوت على الصيدلانيين
and biochemists and clinicians
والكيميائيين الحيويين والاطباء
and I'm sitting there and I'm listening to them
كنت أجلس هناك واراقبهم
and most of the content went straight over my head.
ولم افهم معظم حديثهم
I avoided every science class I ever could.
وتجنبت فهم معظم المصلحات العلمية
But I was watching these people, and I was listening to them,
ولكنني كنت أراقبهم واستمع لهم
and they were saying, "I, I do this, I do that,"
وكانوا يتقاسمون المهام "أنا سأفعل هذا، وأنا سافعل هذا"
and there was a real unfamiliarity between them.
ولكن حقا كان هنالك عدم انسجام بينهم
So at the end of their talk, the panel,
وفي نهاية حديثهم، هيئة الخبراء
they had questions and answers,
كان لديهم اسئلة وأجوبة
and boom, my hand went right up,
وفجأة رفعت يدي
and I get the microphone,
وحصلت على المايكرفون
and I look at them and I say, "Thank you.
ونظرت اليهم وقلت: "شكرا لكم"
Thank you so much for working in ALS.
"شكرا جزيلا لكم، للعمل على مرض الـ ALS"
It means so very much to us."
"انه يعني الكثير لنا"
I said, "But I do have to tell you
وقلت: "ولكن عليّ اخباركم"
that I'm watching your body language
"كنت أراقب لغة جسدكم"
and I'm listening to what you're saying.
"وأسمع ما تقولون"
It just doesn't seem like there's a whole lot of collaboration going on here.
"ولا يبدو أن هنالك الكثير من التعاون هنا"
And not only that, where's the flip chart
"وليس هذا فقط، أين المخططات الزمنية"
with the action items and the follow-up and the accountability?
"مع الاحداث والنتائج والمسؤوليات"
What are you going to do after you leave this room?"
"ماذا ستفعلون بعد مغادرة هذا القاعة ؟"
And then I turned around
وتفلت حولي
and there was about 200 pairs of eyes just staring at me.
ووجدت حوالي 200 عيون تحدق بي
And it was that point that I realized
وفي تلك اللحظة، استنتجت
that I had talked about the elephant in the room.
انني تكلمت عن أمر محرج للجميع
Thus my mission had begun.
وهنا بدأت مهمتي
So over the next couple of years,
لذا في السنتين اللاحقتين
Pete — we've had our highs and our lows.
حظينا مرات بالأمل ومرات اخرى بخيبة الأمل
Pete was put on a compassionate use drug.
بيت بدأ بجرعات من المهدئات
It was hope in a bottle for the whole ALS community.
كان ذلك الأمل الوحيد لمجتمع مرض الـ ALS
It was in a phase III trial.
لقد كان في طور المرحلة الثالثة
Then six months later, the data comes back: no efficacy.
وبعد ستة اشهر جاءت النتائج من دون اي تقدم
We were supposed to have therapies overseas,
كان من المفروض ان نبحث عن العلاج في الخارج
and the rug was pulled out from under us.
ولكن سحب البساط من تحتنا
So for the next two years,
لذا في السنتين التاليتين
we just watched my son be taken away from me,
كنا فقط نشاهد ولدي يأخذ مني
little by little every day.
قليلا قليلا في كل يوم
Two and a half years ago,
منذ سنتان ونصف
Pete was hitting home runs at baseball fields.
كان بيت بارعا في لعبة البيسبول
Today, Pete's completely paralyzed.
اليوم هو مشلول تماما
He can't hold his head up any longer.
ولا يستطيع ان يحمل رأسه بعد الان
He's confined to a motorized wheelchair.
انه يستخدم كرسي الي متحرك
He can no longer swallow or eat.
ولا يستطيع حتى الابتلاع او الأكل
He has a feeding tube.
ووضع له مجرى للطعام
He can't speak.
ولا يستطيع التحدث
He talks with eye gaze technology
ويتكلم باستخدام تكنولوجيا ملاحقة العين
and a speech generating device,
وجهاز توليد الكلام
and we're watching his lungs,
وكنا نراقب رئتيه
because his diaphragm eventually is going to give out
لان حجابه الحاجز سيتوقف يوما ما
and then the decision will be made to put him on a ventilator or not.
وحينها سيتخذ قرار وضعه على جهاز تنفس صناعي او لا
ALS robs the human of all their physical parts, but the brain stays intact.
مرض الـ ALS يسرق كل الأجزاء الحركية من الانسان ولكن العقل يبقى سليما
So July 4th, 2014,
لذا في الرابع من يوليو/تموز 2014
75th year of Lou Gehrig's inspirational speech comes,
75 سنة من خطاب لوو جيرغ التحفيزي
and Pete is asked by MLB.com to write an article in the Bleacher Report.
وطلب موقع اخبار البيسبول MLB من بيت ان يكتب مقالة
And it was very significant, because he wrote it using his eye gaze technology.
ولقد كانت مهمة للغاية لانه استخدم تكنولوجيا ملاحقة العين لكتابتها
Twenty days later, the ice started to fall.
وبعد عشرين يوم بدأ الثلج بالتساقط
On July 27th, Pete's roommate in New York City,
في 27 يوليو/ تموز، زميل بيت في نيويورك
wearing a Quinn For The Win shirt,
يرتدي قميص كوين
signifying Pat Quinn, another ALS patient known in New York,
كوين مريض ALS اخرمعروف في نيويورك
and B.C. shorts
ويرتدي سروال
said, "I'm taking the ALS Ice Bucket Challenge,"
وقال: "انا سأقبل تحدي دلو التلج للـ ALS
picked up the ice, put it over his head.
ورفع الثلج ووضعه على رأسه
"And I'm nominating ..." And he sent it up to Boston.
"وأنا اتحدى ..." وأرسل التحدي لمدينة بوسطن
And that was on July 27th.
وكان هذا في 27 من يوليو/تموز
Over the next couple of days, our news feed
وفي اليومين التاليين اخبارنا
was full of family and friends.
كانت مليئة بالاقارب والاصدقاء
If you haven't gone back, the nice thing about Facebook
ويمكنكم مراجعة ذلك الجميل في فيسبوك
is that you have the dates, you can go back.
بأنه يمكنك العودة للتاريخ لمشاهدة ذلك
You've got to see Uncle Artie's human Bloody Mary.
عليكم مشاهدة العم أرتي وهو يقوم بذلك
I'm telling you, it's one of the best ones,
انه من أفضل المشاهد في تحدي دلو الجليد
and that was probably in day two.
وكان هذا تقريبا في اليوم الثاني
By about day four, Uncle Dave, the webmaster,
وفي حوالي اليوم الرابع العم دايف، مطور الموقع
he isn't on Facebook,
هو ليس على الفيسبوك
and I get a text from him, and it says, "Nancy,
ارسل لي رسالة وقال:
what the hell is going on?"
"نانسي، ماذا يجري"
Uncle Dave gets a hit every time Pete's website
الزيارات على الموقع تضاعفت بشكل كبير
is gone onto, and his phone was blowing up.
وهاتفه لا يتوقف عن الرنين
So we all sat down and we realized,
وجلسنا جميعا ولاحظنا
money is coming in — how amazing.
المال يتدفق من كل مكان يا للروعة
So we knew awareness would lead to funding,
لذا عرفنا ان التوعية ستقود الى التمويل
we just didn't know it would only take a couple of days.
ولكننا لم نتوقع اننا سنحتاج الى يومين فقط
So we got together, put our best 501(c)(3)s on Pete's website,
لذا تكاتفنا لنضع افضل المحتويات على موقع بيت
and off we went.
وبذلنا قصارى جهدنا
So week one, Boston media.
ففي الأسبوع الأول، تغطى من قبل اعلام بوسطن
Week two, national media.
في الأسبوع الثاني تغطى من الاعلام الوطني
It was during week two that our neighbor next door
وخلال الأسبوع الثاني قامت جارتنا
opened up our door and threw a pizza
برمي صحن بيتزا من الباب
across the kitchen floor, saying,
خلال فتحة المطبخ، وقالت:
"I think you people might need food in there."
"اعتقد ياناس أنكم بحاجة للطعام بالداخل"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Week three, celebrities — Entertainment Tonight,
الاسبوع الثالث، المشاهير انترنيرمينت تونايت
Access Hollywood.
وبرنامج اكسس هوليوود
Week four, global — BBC, Irish Radio.
الاسبوع 4 ،عالميا بي بي سي ، الراديو الايرلندي
Did anyone see "Lost In Translation"?
هل شاهدتم فلم "ضاع في الترجمة"
My husband did Japanese television.
زوجي اجرى مقابلة من التلفزيون الياباني
It was interesting.
لقد كان ممتعا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And those videos, the popular ones.
واشهر الفيديوهات
Paul Bissonnette's glacier video, incredible.
فيديو الجليد الخاص بباول بيسونتي انه رائع
How about the redemption nuns of Dublin?
وايضا فيديو الدوبلين ؟
Who's seen that one?
من شاهده ؟
It's absolutely fantastic.
انه رائع جدا
J.T., Justin Timberlake.
جوستين تيمبرليك
That's when we knew, that was a real A-list celebrity.
لقد كانت قائمة المشاهير الأولى
I go back on my texts, and I can see
لقد شاهدت هاتفي
"JT! JT!" My sister texting me.
ورايت رسائل أختي
Angela Merkel, the chancellor of Germany.
أنجيلا ميركل، المستشارة الألمانية
Incredible.
مذهل
And the ALS patients,
ومرضى الـ ALS
you know what their favorite ones are, and their families'?
هل تعلمون ما الفيديو المفضل لديهم والمفضل لعائلتهم؟
All of them.
جميعهم
Because this misunderstood and underfunded "rare" disease,
لأن هذا المرض النادر والغير مفهوم والغير مدعوم
they just sat and watched people saying it over and over: "ALS, ALS."
فقط جلسوا يشاهدون الناس يقولون: "ALS ، ALS"
It was unbelievable.
لقد كان شيئا لا يصدق
And those naysayers,
وهؤلاء الرافضين
let's just talk a couple of stats, shall we?
دعونا نأخذ بعض الاحصائيات ؟
Okay, so the ALS Association,
لذا منظمة الـ ALS
they think by year end, it'll be 160 million dollars.
يتوقعون أن يصلوا للـ 160 مليون مع نهاية السنة
ALS TDI in Cambridge,
ALS TDI في كامريدج
they raised three million dollars.
وصلوا للثلاثة ملايين دولار
Well, guess what?
حسنا، واحذروا ماذا؟
They had a clinical trial for a drug that they've been developing.
ولديهم دواء تجريبي، كانوا يعملون على تطويره
It was on a three-year track for funding.
لقد كان بعد ثلاثة سنوات من التبرعات
Two months.
بشهرين
It's coming out starting in two months.
بدا بالظهور خلال شهرين
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And YouTube has reported
ولقد اظهر يوتيوب تقارير
that over 150 countries have posted Ice Bucket Challenges for ALS.
انه اكثر من 150 دولة قامت بتحدي دلو الثلج
And Facebook, 2.5 million videos,
وفي فيسبوك 2.5 مليون فيديو
and I had the awesome adventure
ولقد حظيت بتجربة رائعة
visiting the Facebook campus last week,
بزيارة حرم فيسبوك الاسبوع الماضي
and I said to them, "I know what it was like in my house.
وقلت لهم: "أعلم كيف كان الوضع في منزلي في تلك الاثناء"
I can't imagine what it was like around here."
"ولا أستطيع تخيّل ماكان يحدث هنا"
All she said was, "Jaw-dropping."
قالت لي: "كنا مندهشين للغاية"
And my family's favorite video?
والفيديو المفضل لعائلتي :
Bill Gates.
بيل غيتس
Because the night Pete was diagnosed,
لان الليلة التي شخص بها بيت
he told us that he was going to get ALS in front of philanthropists like Bill Gates,
لأنه قال سيعرض مرض الـ ALS على المتبرعين امثال بيل غيتس
and he did it.
ولقد فعلها حقا
Goal number one, check.
الهدف الأول، تم تحقيقه
Now on to the treatment and cure.
الان، الى العلاج والشفاء
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So okay, after all of this ice,
حسنا، الان بعد كل هذا الثلج
we know that it was much more
راينا انه كان كثير للغاية
than just pouring buckets of ice water over your head,
من مجرد سكب ماء جليدي فوق رأسك
and I really would like to leave you
اود فعلا أن أخبركم قبل أن انتهي
with a couple of things that I'd like you to remember.
بشيئين مهمين أود ان تتذكروهما
The first thing is,
أول شيء
every morning when you wake up,
في كل صباح عندما تستيقظ
you can choose to live your day in positivity.
يمكنك اختيار أن تعيش يومك بايجابية
Would any of you blame me
هل كان سيلومني أحد منكم
if I just was in the fetal position
لو انطويت على نفسي
and pulled the covers over my head every day?
وغطيت راسي كل يوم؟
No, I don't think anybody would blame me,
لا، لا اعتقد ان احدا منكم سيلومني
but Pete has inspired us to wake up
ولكن بيت حفزنا للاستيقاظ
every morning and be positive and proactive.
كل يوم وكان ايجابيا وسباقا
I actually had to ditch support groups
كان في الحقيقة يجب عليّ طلب الدعم
because everybody was in there saying that
لان جميع من كان هناك قال ذلك
spraying their lawns with chemicals,
انهم يرشون اعشابهم بالمواد الكيميائية
that's why they got ALS,
لذلك أصيبوا بمرض الـ ALS
and I was like, "I don't think so,"
وكنت لا اعتقد ان ذلك صحيحا
but I had to get away from the negativity.
وكان عليّ الابتعاد عن السلبية
The second thing I want to leave you with
الشيء الثاني الذي أريد أن اخبركم به
is the person at the middle of the challenge
عندما يكون الشخص في منتصف التحدي
has to be willing to have the mental toughness
يجب ان يتحلى برجاحة العقل
to put themselves out there.
حتى يتخلصوا من المشكلة
Pete still goes to baseball games
مازل بيت يذهب للعبة البيسبول
and he still sits with his teammates in the dugout,
ويجلس جانب زملائه في قواعد الاحتياط
and he hangs his gravity feed bag
ويحمل معه حقيبه التغذية الخاصة به
right on the cages.
في المكان المناسب
You'll see the kids, they're up there hanging it up.
وسترا بعض الاولاد حوله يسألونه:
"Pete, is that okay?" "Yup."
"بيت، هل هذا صحيح؟" "نعم"
And then they put it right into his stomach.
ومن ثم يضعونها على معدته
Because he wants them to see what the reality of this is,
لانه يريدهم أن يروا حقيقه الأمر
and how he's never, ever going to give up.
وكيف أنه لن يستسلم أبدا
And the third thing I want to leave you with:
وثالث شيء، أريد أن أخبركم به:
If you ever come across a situation
اذا مررت يوما بحالة
that you see as so unacceptable,
ووجدتها مرفوضة للغاية
I want you to dig down as deep as you can
اطلب منك ان تحفر بأعمق ما تستطيع
and find your best mother bear
بحثا عن أفضل حل مناسب
and go after it.
وتسعى للوصول اليه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
I know that I'm running over,
اعلم انه قد انتهى وقتي
but I've got to leave you with this:
ولكن عليّ أن أترككم بهذه:
the gifts that my son has given me.
الهدايا التي منحني اياها ابني
I have had 29 years
لقد حظيت بـ 29 عاما
of having the honor of being the mother
بشرف كوني والدة
of Pete Frates.
بيت فريتس
Pete Frates has been inspiring and leading his whole life.
بيت فريتس، كان ملهما وقائدا طوال حياته
He's thrown out kindness,
لقد كان شديد اللطف
and all that kindness has come back to him.
وكل لطفه عاد اليه
He walks the face of the Earth right now and knows why he's here.
هو يمشي على ظهر الأرض ويعلم لماذا هو هنا
What a gift.
ما أروع هذه الهدية
The second thing that my son has given me
الهدية الاخرى التي وهبها لي ابني
is he's given me my mission in life.
انه اعطاني مهمتي في هذه الحياة
Now I know why I'm here.
الان اعلم لماذا انا هنا
I'm going to save my son,
سأقوم بانقاذ ابني
and if it doesn't happen in time for him,
واذا لم استطع أن أفعل ذلك
I'm going to work so that no other mother
ساسعى للعمل لكي لا يتكرر مع ام أخرى
has to go through what I'm going through.
ما أصابني
And the third thing, and last but not least
وثالث شيء ، واخيرا وليس أخرا
gift that my son has given me,
هدية وهبني اياها ابني
as an exclamation point
وكعلامة فارقة
to the miraculous month
الشهر المعجزة
of August 2014:
في شهر أغسطس/أب 2014
That girlfriend that he went to get on the night of diagnosis is now his wife,
صديقته التي ذهب لاحضارها في ليلة تشخيصه هي زوجته الأن
and Pete and Julie have given me my granddaughter, Lucy Fitzgerald Frates.
بيت وجولي اعطوني حفيدتي، لوسي فيتزجير فراتس
Lucy Fitzgerald Frates came two weeks early
لوسي فيتزجير ولدت قبل أسبوعين من موعدها
as the exclamation point
كعلامة فارقة
on August 31st, 2014.
في 31 أغسطس/أب 2014
And so —
لذا..
(Applause) —
(تصفيق)
And so let me leave you with Pete's words of inspiration
دعوني اتركم بكلمات بيت المشجعة
that he would use to classmates, coworkers and teammates.
التي كان يستخدمها لزملائه
Be passionate.
كن صبورا
Be genuine.
كن اصيلا
Be hardworking.
كن مجدا
And don't forget to be great.
ولا تنسى أن تكون عظيما
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم (تصفيق)